Well, as you saw on the first day when
I talked about new ventures and the elements that have
to come together to have a successful venture,
and Bob also said it's the people issues that
tend to sink ventures more often than not.
It's not the technology, it's
not the funding, it's people issues.
So it seems very important then that we
have something that talks about people issues and
organizations.
And tonight we have a panel, unfortunately one
of whom is sick and not able to come.
But Vivian Batali is our moderator.
I met Vivian a few years ago.
I'm on the board of a public company that
is still run by one of the founders, and I'm
chair of the nomination and governance committee.
So when we were looking to expand
the board, that was what our committee does.
So after doing a search, et cetera, we
had some candidates, and I met with Vivian.
And it became clear pretty soon in talking
to her that she was a great candidate for
a founders, for any company,
but a founder one in particular.
I remember we talked about the things you'd
worked on with a senior management, and at
least two of the three you worked
on, I think I knew the founders.
And I think I had incorporated one of those companies.
And so the idea that we'd have
a board member with HR experience, organization experience,
that knows how to deal with a
founder-led company that was growing seemed really great.
So I couldn't think of a
better candidate to put this panel together.
And last year I did the
dope slap and said, Vivian's the person.
And I convinced her, again
with our highly paid compensation.
These beautiful water bottles.
And Vivian assembled a panel of other people
that she thought would be useful in the organization
and people issues.
And so I'm going to turn it over to Vivian.
And we're going to, we want to make it interactive.
So if you have questions,
we hope you have a bunch.
Put your hands up.
We'll have the mics run around.
We do have some questions sort of pre-canned.
But if you have some issues, just say them.
And we'll get them.
And we'll see what we can do with them.
So without further ado, Vivian, thank you once again.
Thanks.
We did this last year.
And we really enjoyed it.
And what made it really
great was people were very interactive.
And we do have questions that
people have submitted here ahead of time.
But I think it might work best free form
with people raising their hands on what you want
to talk about.
The areas that, as many people are
building their company, they're building their business,
they're building their business.
And I think it's really important that people
are interested in really what you do as a
founder, early stage.
What are the things that you need
to do in terms of building your organization?
How do you hire people?
How do you pay people?
How do you deal with problems?
All those, hopefully, we'll be able
to touch on with you tonight.
We have different experiences.
I'll tell you a little bit about my experience.
I worked many, many years.
Right now, I'm not working full time anymore.
I have a small consulting practice where I do
really just the work that I like to do,
which is working with people, building their
business, or helping people grow in their
roles, particularly when someone is new
to a position, particularly if they're working
in an HR or people function.
I like to have people get started doing that.
And then I'm on two public company boards with Joe.
I'm on the NetScout system boards.
God bless you over there.
Fantastic.
Thank you.
And also Progress Software.
And then I also work on a couple of nonprofits.
I work on Entrepreneurship for All,
which some people may know about.
Works outside the Boston area, helping entrepreneurs
get going and help them get their business
launched.
And then I work with a company,
an organization called Family Services of Merrimack Valley,
which is a nonprofit that helps
the disadvantaged in the greater rural areas.
And I've been working with them
for a couple of years now.
I've been working with them
So it's a little bit about me.
So I'm going to turn
it over to my colleagues here.
We've worked together before, and I thought that
they would be able to provide a different
view of some of the questions you might have
that I might have, and I think really highly
of them.
And I know that they'll offer a lot tonight.
So I'll start with Kim here.
Hi.
So I'm Kim Crowley.
I've had the pleasure of working for Viv as
one of my first bosses in my career, my
HR career.
So 25 years of HR experience.
And I've been working for Viv for about 30 years.
So I've been working for Viv for about 30 years.
So I'm Kim Crowley.
I've had the pleasure of working for Viv as
one of my first bosses in my career, my
HR career.
So 25 years of HR experience.
I am a VP of HR with Thermo Fisher Scientific.
I started with them in 2010.
I sidestepped and went to a much smaller company
a few years ago by the name of Azenta Life
Sciences.
So I've always really kind of grown up
in much more of the life science industry.
I did go back to my home office
and went to a company called Zenta Life Sciences.
And I've been working for them for about 30 years.
So I'm going to turn it over to Kim here.
Hi.
So I'm Kim Crowley.
I've had the pleasure of working for Viv as
one of my first bosses in my career, my
HR career.
So 25 years of HR experience.
I started with them in 2010.
I sidestepped and went to a much smaller company
a few years ago by the name of Azenta Life
Sciences.
So I've always really kind of grown up
in much more of the life science industry.
I did go back to Thermo Fisher.
So they are now.
And, you know, just I have on the flip
side, while Viv has had smaller companies, you know,
co-founders, I've been on the flip side of
it with larger companies as we start to look,
you know, very acquisitive companies, start to
look at the business as a whole.
And I think that's a really good
example of how we can work together.
So I'm Kim Crowley.
I'm a VP of HR.
And I think that's a really good
example of how we can work together.
And, you know, just I have on the flip
side, while Viv has had smaller companies, you know,
co-founders, I've been on the flip side of
it with larger companies as we start to look,
you know, very acquisitive companies,
start to look at acquisitions.
What do we look for?
How do we handle different scenarios?
And how do we introduce them into a larger company?
So I'm very happy to be
here and looking forward to the conversation.
Hi.
I'm Michelle Bonifant.
I, too, am very happy
to be here with you today.
So similar to Kim, I
started my career working for Vivian.
She was one of my first, I call, real
bosses when I was toying with following in the legal
field or if I would head into technology.
My career has spanned high tech.
So I have spent all
of my space in high tech.
I currently am the senior director
of global people operations for QuickBase.
But I pivoted away from
HR for a number of years.
So although I started in that
space, I had an aptitude for technology.
And I leaned into the go-to-market
space with a human capital management organization.
I worked for Ultimate Software.
They merged with a company called Chroma.
I'm a senior director of
the Global People Operations for QuickBase.
I'm also the CEO of the
company called Kronos to become UKG.
And I had the privilege of working
with hundreds of companies, small companies, mid-sized companies,
large companies operationally to understand their
infrastructure and how to set them up
for success.
So I'm happy to be here with you today.
I'm happy to share the learnings
that I found along the way.
I've participated in many different
mergers and acquisitions of small companies.
I've worked with a number of companies,
large companies, and really put that infrastructure
in place.
Okay.
Thank you very much.
So I'll just tell you a little
bit about how I always approached my work.
I never ever thought I wanted to work in
a capacity where I would be doing people or
HR work.
But I started out really more in
public relations, marketing, and what have you.
But I ended up being a person
where people came to for advice and counsel.
And I started to see that you could
really help people and help people be more effective
by providing clarity often around what needed to
be done or even just explaining a policy
that I might know something about.
I was the writer in the company I worked
for initially, and so in addition to doing some
of the public relations work that I did.
I ended up writing the onboarding materials
and the company manuals and all of that.
And so I got to see that you could
just have such an impact by helping people realize what
organizations wanted them to do, but
also helping facilitate them be successful.
And I was very fortunate in I worked at
and grew companies in the companies that I worked
for.
And I shared similar values with the founders
of those companies, the leaders of those companies.
And it's my belief that that's
what helped make those companies successful.
Certainly it was the products
and it was the right market.
But when you have the right combination
of people with similar values and similar goals,
and you put those together, you can work miracles.
And so I'd like to see that.
En suite guys, you'll talk about your
acquired interests, our common interests, executive interests,
and views.
prochaine topics may you want to talk about?
Thank you for asking those brings Kim these topics.
I think again, that older than anyone, Ifachour
5000 more questions to return to and the conversation
we did later.
the question.
Michel As wells I'd like to begin by saying
that we're in the middle of a second quarter
in the last dozen terms, or two minutes.
We're still in the early 80s.
well so hopefully we can can help you
with things that you want to talk about
tonight so I don't know if anybody wants to
start off or I can read off one of
the questions here we can give you some
we can start from there how about I do
that we got one okay got a question
when should you start thinking about that HR function and in order to keep that DNA that you have with the
special spark that you want to instill in the company how do you ensure that goes on even with investors coming along
okay I think that you know
whenever you're starting anything right I think
if it's your product or if it's your company
um
you know typically maybe you're doing that
on your own but most like you're
doing with one or two other people at
least to start I think it's important
for you to talk about what's important
to you and to make sure that the people
that you're working with particularly
I've been in situations where there's
been you know co-founders co-founders
that co-managed and you know
built their companies from there and
having alignment
I think around what's important
in a company transition see people's
Fragen explains what we call as
changing your portfolio in a company transition
important to you, important around what you're
trying to develop in terms of the quality
that you want to put into it, what
are the values around what you're producing, and then
how do you operate together, right?
What things are important?
Trust is something that gets built over time.
If you're going into business with someone,
hopefully that you have some measure of trust
or understanding there, but I
think it starts very early, right?
And I think whoever builds that organization, he
or she, being conscious about it from the
beginning, particularly if it's something you
want to grow and expand, you're going
to create an environment and you're going
to create a livelihood, hopefully for yourself
and for others.
You want to make sure that that has
elements that not only are sustainable, but also things
that you believe in.
And in terms of where, I
think you start that early on, right?
And then I think when you bring people
into an organization, I did consulting with companies
that were really small.
I used to say that my rule of thumb was
around 50 people or more, you needed some sort of
help in that area.
It could be maybe somebody outside.
It could be an advisor.
It could be family.
You need somebody outside your circle to help
you figure out how to structure, to help you
figure out how to build your business.
And maybe it's even a little smaller than
that, depending on what the nature of the
work is that you have.
And then I think as you go through it,
how you hire is probably one of the most important
things.
Whether you're a small company.
Whether you're a large company.
What that process is and how you vet
people and how you treat people in that process.
Whether or not you hire them or not
is all a part of creating that culture.
I also think that early on, it's
important for companies to have a cadence.
Just like one boss that used to
say that managing was often like parenting.
Right?
Right.
And sometimes if you have regular routines
around how you do things, it becomes predictable,
but it also gives people a sense of security.
And that you do that as you parent, but
you also do that when you manage and you build
an organization.
And then I think as you go
through that, you go through a lot of...
You make mistakes.
You know sometimes it's their hiring mistakes.
Sometimes they're directional mistakes.
Right?
And having the ability with your team to
figure out how to move on from that starts
to create the environment and then
you build upon it from there.
And I think it changed.
I mean I saw...
Largest growth I saw was probably from
a company of 55 people to probably around...
I guess we were about
2,000 people when RSA was sold.
I worked at a company called
RSA Security that was bought by EMC.
And I think that's what I saw.
It was a really...
At each stage of growth, it was
sometimes a different company and you needed different
things.
But I think what was important is we came
back to the values that we had around how
we wanted to run our business, how we
wanted to treat one another, what was important,
what we measured.
I would say the organizations that worked best for
me and the ones that I was most proud
to be associated with were the ones that were...
Yeah.
The ones that were organizations of
high achievement, but also human kindness.
And I don't think that they're mutually exclusive.
Very high standards.
I think that you don't compromise those.
But I do think that
you still can have a how.
And even if you have the tough things that
you have to do in an organization, we were
just talking about that now.
Yeah.
I think there's a how in terms you can treat
people even if you have to make a change in
the organization or if you had to do a
workforce reduction or whatever the case may be, where
you can still treat people with
respect and kindness even in difficult times.
So my point of view on that question, I
ask these guys to jump in a little bit.
I think you asked a question also around culture
and I think when you think about how do you
build culture?
How do you maintain that as you start your organization?
It's really building that foundation.
So even just as simple as what is your
mission statement and something that I think you and
the core leadership team can build upon
so that you reemphasize that as you continue
to grow.
What is your mission?
What was it that you were set out to accomplish?
And even a company like Thermo
Fisher is at the 130,000 employees.
Our mission is to make the world healthier, cleaner, safer.
And why it is so critical and it's so
important is because even on our worst days when I'm
trying to motivate finance professionals, how
do you contribute to the overall culture
of the organization?
It comes down to a patient and saving lives.
And the patient becomes your family member.
It's your mother, your brother, your sister, your child.
And that's what culture does.
It brings you back.
And it makes...
For you...
Yeah.
For you as entrepreneurs, it makes your mission
and what you're trying to do just as important
to your employees as it is to you.
Right?
So you use that as a tool to
motivate your workforce, but also to attract your talent.
So what I've noticed growing up in HR over
the past couple of decades is that the younger
generations, they want something that they can connect to.
They want to know that what they're doing is...
Yeah.
It's symbolic and it's important to them.
And so when you think about culture and
how do you articulate your culture and what you're
trying to do, keep that in mind and how
do you do that and you leverage that brand for
your people purposes as well.
I agree with what Kim stated.
So I was actually focusing on the
culture piece of the question that you asked.
I can tell you that one of the companies...
The one that I'm working with is a company called...
The one that I am most proud
to have worked for and worked with.
Started relatively small with a problem.
The founder worked for ADP and he
was unhappy with how things were being processed.
He was a salesperson.
He thought he had a better way
to create a product that companies could use.
And so he took himself and a gentleman that
he worked with and just really kind of took
kind of out of his garage, started a
product with his brother who was more the technical
piece.
But I think what I admired most about
their philosophy and how they approached it, they
really cared about people.
It was people first.
And the motto was that if you took care
of your people, your people would take care of
your customers and everything else would work out.
And it seems very simple, but it was true.
And he never shied from that.
He didn't formally hire an HR
person to kind of run the business.
But what he did do was he hired people
who believed in people and they were hard workers.
They were really high achievers.
And then naturally what happened was people
kind of gravitated to the roles within the
business that they had.
They had their strengths and weaknesses with.
And then he hired over time where there were gaps.
But the philosophy never changed.
And watching that company from a very small
number of people and revenue to expand to
be a significant number of
people, revenue and ultimately sold.
It was public at one point.
It became private.
It was then picked up and bought by a
private equity firm that basically wanted it for 20
years.
And they weren't willing to sell it
because of the people and their connection.
The profitability was extraordinary and
it was shared throughout the organization.
So I think Kim is right.
I think that you have to have a mission statement.
You have to have something that your
organization ties to that throughout the business.
So for me, I wasn't in HR.
But it was something I always thought of.
I knew that I was going to
be taken care of as an employee.
And so I took care of my customers.
And so as a result, revenue was generated.
So I think it's very important to align with culture.
Thank you very much.
Most of the professional relationships within
the small teams should be a practice.
Thank you.
I think that in a small
business, you're going to have that.
I think that it can get difficult, particularly friendships.
I think what helps with that, what helps
it work, is a level of understanding about what's
going on in the organization.
It's not just about the business.
It's about the people.
For example, you work in a military setting.
And there, it's an issue of decentralization of business
in a state system.
It's not necessarily a statement, as Marc said.
But it can be powerful.
And I think that's what we'll have
to look for, in terms of meeting.
you've worked with before or what
have you. And you know those those
relationships may have started out as
friendships and then had a professional
component or vice versa right. But
I think the role clarity is really
important and also norms of behavior
and really having discussions not waiting
for those to evolve. If you decide
you're going to go into business with with
someone you've developed something with for
example. I think talking about that is
is really really really important and
setting that up. As organizations evolve
you know I think there has to be sort
of rules of the road for how people operate.
I mean we always we work together we
are very social we're still we're very good
friends now. And but when we work
together our friend it was we had a
collegial work environment.
The friendships really developed more
later and the friendships developed out
of really mutual respect and
from working together and achieving something
together building something together. I mean
once you've had the opportunity to
build something together it's successful. I
mean it's you've worked and there's
nothing like it. And that my
best experiences were we're really building
organizations that that could thrive. The
the company that that I grew up
with was the University of Texas. I
mean I grew up in a very well-established
company. I grew up in a very well-established
institution. I grew up at I was there
10 years and the company was sold on the
week of my 10 year anniversary there
which was and my birthday. And it was
just one of those things and I but I was
so proud of it. You know and and I will
tell you I remember crying that day
with my children when that happened because
I I was I didn't spend as much time
at home often as I did at work. It's just
the nature of what I did. And you
know I'm telling my kids this is you know
part of your legacy now you know it's
like. Well you were fine you know you're
just a guilty working mother. But you
know having that that pride in building
something together right. So I think
having a dialogue around it and early
days doing that and establishing who
does what. And also knowing sometimes
when to back away. Right I
have seen a couple of situations
where I consulted where you know
there were co-co-CEOs for example that really
doesn't typically work very well.
You know, one person
usually needs to be in charge.
It's not that the other person doesn't
add equal value, and that's often
why you often have your CTO person
and maybe your person that runs the other
side. The last company
I worked at, the founder never
wanted to run the company. He just
wanted to be the evangelist for
the product that he helped develop,
and he decided that early on,
so there were other people that came in
and ran that organization.
I hope that helps
answer your question.
What are the differences between founders and co-founders?
So that's
number one question. Second one is
actually, like, in terms of
for, like, a startup company,
sometimes there are high roles, so you need
to bring a lot of people in.
And sometimes you're not sure
the energy that you need that person
to work out, you know,
working hard. So I wonder
whether, in terms of how
to structure that kind of relationship
is going to be
like a, you know, a high-paying
six months or a year or three months, which type of the reason
of the person trying to figure out where is the fit or not.
And in terms of conversation, life or equity arrangement-wise, is the best thing, is the
only way to kind of make this kind of arrangement or what other arrangement makes sense.
That's a lot of good ones.
Yeah, I know. I don't
know where to start with that.
So what I guess I will say is that sometimes I think it's a good situation,
even not in just a founding situation, to sort of try before you buy, if you will.
Particularly if you're uncertain.
Yeah.
You know, sometimes people are
not sure about that person's capability.
You know, sometimes people may represent their
skills different, you know, better than they are.
You know, and so if you can have someone come in as a consultant, I think, you know, depending on how what
the nature is that they're providing the service about, I usually could assess that, I would say, in less than three months.
Sometimes a day.
You know, sometimes you would know.
But I trust my intuitive judgment on that.
That was one of my things
that I was always good at doing.
But I think that within three months, I mean, that's why
in the past people used to have these 90-day probation periods.
You know, when people came in, they
don't do that so much at work anymore.
But you can usually tell if
people are going to be contributing.
And most importantly, you're going to be able
to tell if you're going to be contributing.
And so that's a good thing.
You're going to be able to tell if you're
going to have good give and take with them.
And so, you know, to
bring in someone in that respect.
And then it depends on what you can afford.
It depends what that person's expertise is.
I think early on, if you can do it in a way that it's, you know, some sort
of monetary compensation, you know, versus stock or anything like that, I wouldn't do anything like that early on.
If you're limited in money, you know,
you're going to have to do it.
You know, you're going to have to do it.
You can try to negotiate something.
Or if someone really does want the job, they'll maybe accept, you know, a little bit
of a less of a consulting fee if they think that you might be hiring them.
So I hope that answers some of your questions.
In the beginning, your question was
about who should, about co-founder title.
Yes.
Co-founder, co-founder.
Is that kind of a difference?
Or like let's say we have someone
who joined a couple of years ago.
Yes.
a couple of day?
As most money you spend there times.
Yes.
It să medicality output there as a much
better possible way to do what you've done?
Given benefits333 00 cas a couple of months created than-
姐姐吃了
What is a co-founder?
In that case, the founder and co-founder...
It can be ambiguous.
I think that in the
situations where I've seen the co-founders,
they really did come in together.
It wasn't that somebody came and asked for that.
I personally have not seen that.
I guess what I would say
is it would depend on the value
that that person was bringing in.
If he or she had
an expertise that you really needed
to make your business be successful,
and it complimented you,
then that might be something I would do.
But I don't know that I
would give it away right away.
I think I would take the
time to get to know that person,
whether it's coming in and working as a consultant,
whether it's problem-solving on something,
whether it's working together.
I also think that in that whole recruitment process,
if it's a small organization that you have,
or whenever we hired executives,
I would always have more
than one course or interview inside,
but I'd always try to take people out to dinner.
Or an informal environment.
I used to always look for
how well people treated the way
they were.
I would look at the staff in a restaurant
when we were going to hire an executive.
You know, did they treat that person with respect?
How did they behave around others?
Because someone can interview very well,
but you might miss some of the subtleties
for how their human interaction is.
And so that's what I would advise.
I would take my time and try
to really get to know the person.
And the whole person, not just what they're bringing
to the table or their
particular technical expertise or skill set.
One in the back there.
Gentleman back there.
Thank you for your answers.
I have a question regarding your experience
that you mentioned in very good acquisitions and that sort.
So what are your .
I asked you for that .
I know that not everybody might know
that you might have found regarding
or for a startup that's trying to be destructive
against these big, large companies.
But at the same time, is basic battles
in being acquired by those large companies.
What advice do you have for those startups
to be disruptive and to
kind of dominate in that sense
and overtake those large companies?
So you want me to take this one?
Oh, I thought you'd put you.
So being with a very large company.
And when I think about the competitive landscape.
And so right now, I'll
give you a real time story.
We're a multinational company.
We have a very large
business that we do in China.
And the China competition can do it better and faster.
And they're small.
They're much smaller than us.
So just I was in China over the summer.
And we got the opportunity to go meet
with a bunch of customers.
And the difference is that our.
Our sell is size and scale.
We can service anything you need.
The problem with doing business with a larger company
is the pace is slow and the rigidity is large.
So the smaller companies build on the relationship
and how flexible, nimble, and fast they can be.
And that's the difference.
It really is in terms of customer service.
And then there's always different dynamics
that are playing from an economic standpoint.
That you just got to get ahead
and kind of be on top of
and think about.
But frankly, those are the
things that being a large company,
it irritates us.
It's like, oh, we just can't move fast enough.
Or we cannot accommodate for this particular customer.
Because that would mean we have to extend that
to other customers or things of that nature.
But that's one thing.
And then certainly, depending upon what is going to be,
what you're selling, it's going to be,
whether it's quality.
What we find with the smaller companies, it's usually price.
They can do it for a better price.
So if it's a good enough type of product
where the customer's looking for,
they're not necessarily going to go for our bigger quality
product that we've invested a lot of R&D dollars in.
But they're going to look
for the good enough product that's
at a better price point.
I would say also, one of the companies
that I'm on the board for.
We've done a lot of research.
The company's been around a long time.
It's an infrastructure company.
And our direction now is growing through acquisition.
And we've been very selective
and disciplined in that process.
The prices for companies over private or ones
that are being divested or whatever
is because of all the
money that's been in the market.
It's been really hard to compete sometimes with,
with what private equity could do.
But what I would say
is that with the right approach,
when we've been acquiring, we've been really careful
to keep the right talent, particularly the people
that understand the technology and whatever.
And many times, the people that have founded these companies
have a very strong following of the people that
work for them, right?
And so in order to
retain them, we've been very careful.
And also make sure you get
the most out of that acquisition
investment to make sure that you're keeping a founder,
at least for a period of
time, and make it a win-win situation.
That, I think, works the best.
And the smart companies, I think, understand that and know
how to make it attractive for people to stay.
I would agree with that.
So in my current organization, it's
a strategy that we have.
So rather than building out the product offering
that we have now, we're looking outside
to see what products can be complementary or for something
that the customer will utilize.
We acquired a company last year ago, June.
And the revenue component on that organization
is extraordinary.
It ran intact.
It was a separate part of the business
for almost the better part of
a year so that we could really
assess the talent that was there.
The founder is still there.
He had a great say in how the operation would
come into the business.
And it's only been the past
six months that it's now that,
I would say, outside of the G&A functions,
So I think there's lots of opportunity
there, and I think, from my experience, companies
want their acquisition to be successful.
And the talent and the people that are
there, oftentimes it's not simply the product that's
the most important piece.
Yeah.
A lot of times, too, I think if you do
it the right way, you look at the talent that
you're bringing in through an acquisition,
and sometimes you have better talent that
you're hiring, and you may
not have the same talent inside.
And it's not always popular to do that,
but I can think of organizations that, in the
past, I was a part of and we made acquisitions.
I actually made changes on my staff because
the people that we got through the acquisition
just had a better skill set.
And that's never an easy conversation, but at the
end of the day, you have to do what's
best for the business.
And you've got to go with...
As America.
Yeah.
And I think that's what's really important, is
that you have to take the people that you
are hiring and make them your own.
And I think that's the best way to do it.
I think that's the best way to do it.
Thank you.
Thank you, Shari.
My question is, I've been very
impressed with how people relate to us.
As a founder, I actually find myself to be more...
I have valued the relationship more than the interests.
That's just how I feel.
I don't want to be the one who's like, I'm
not going to be the one who's going to do this.
I'm just going to be the
one who's going to do this.
And I think that's the best thing.
Yeah.
I think that's really important.
And in that sense, is it important
to have yourидados sometimes raised, making them
your own?
Or sometimes are you making a class application
work or are you changing some of that...
Are you looking at some of this sort of
or not looking at some of this sort of management
where you're the founder, right?
you making them your own?
And usually with that kind
of background, I 죽 último interface.
come across as, you know,
you're not setting enough boundaries.
I think, you know, some founders, like,
founders come from a variety of, you know,
boxes, like, they're different.
So maybe there's a team or something that I
think that would very close to that kind of confidence
will grow up to where it's going to be
a very mindful, you know, people in my situation.
Yeah.
Thank you.
So here, the best advice that I can give
you is, and it's interesting because I just had
this conversation with one of the executives that
we have, and I think the best thing that
you can do, we try and try oftentimes to
look at the faults that we have and change them,
and there's going to come a certain point
in your career where you have to step back
and be very self-aware of who you are.
And you look at the strengths, and
you look at where you have opportunities.
Right?
And so you said, you know, oftentimes you
may not have the boundaries that you need.
That's who you are.
You know, so even when you think about that
from a leader standpoint, that is who you are.
So you say, okay, these are
the things that I'm really good at.
These are the things that I need some help with.
And you go higher, and you put people
that trust, that fill in those gaps around you.
So, you know, my advice to my colleague as
we were talking about it, he's incredibly strategic in nature.
He's very broad thinking.
His issue is that he has
a really hard time bringing strategy.
Execution and mobilizing his workforce.
And so instead of sitting there and trying to change
him forever around how do you articulate that strategy better,
it's we try to put folks around
him that he trusts that are execution-oriented,
and then they go off and
they mobilize the rest of the workforce.
So you might want to think about, you know, how do you
complement your own style with people that are a little bit different,
that you trust their advice, you
know, because that's going to be hard.
Right.
Those conversations will be difficult, but you
know that when the person comes to you,
okay, they mean it with the best of intentions, and
they can balance, you know, some of that out for you.
Yeah, I agree with that, too.
I think you, we are who we are, right?
And so I can think of a point in my
career when I first got into a more senior role,
I started to be, tried to
be somebody different than who I was.
You know, when I was,
you know, more hard-nosed about things, for
lack of a better way to describe it,
and I didn't trust my intuitive
judgment as much as I used to,
and I wasn't as effective, right?
So I think, you know, if that's who
you are, I think Kim's advice is good advice.
You know, understand who you are, and,
you know, we change a little bit,
but, you know, over time, we're pretty fully formed by
the time we get to around 30, 35, even more.
When you're over 50.
And then you just hire to your compliment, and
take trusted advice of people that are different from you
and have a different point of view.
But I think that, you know, understanding who you are
and having people probably appreciate the fact
that you are like you are, right?
And that you do show, it
sounds like you show empathy and consistency.
Yeah.
And consideration, very much so.
And that's a gift.
It is a gift.
It's also, you know what, it's a muscle.
So the more you use it,
the better you'll get at it.
So the more you recognize that that's not your strength,
and you need to lean
on someone else to do it,
the better you'll get at being able to recognize that,
and it won't be as painful for you to do.
Because I think when you
do have that element of empathy,
it's hard to push people away at first.
But just know that you're doing better by them
by putting them in front of people who are better
able to lead them in the direction that they need to,
and then you can focus on
the things that you need to.
You'll get better at it, I promise.
We have one way in the back there.
She's waiting.
Yeah.
Getting your workout tonight.
I know.
I already did.
I'm moving forward.
Hi.
My question is around female founders
and balancing some of the traits that some
executives might not find as common with founders
and how to balance being
yourself and being the other person
that some people are used
to, especially when you're raising.
And when you're scaling or hiring senior
members to join your team and the board?
That's a different question.
Is this idea more technical about as
a startup there are no processes in place?
Maybe you just set up milestones and goals
for your employees that change regularly based on performance?
But at what point should we actually put that down
to paper and start writing processes for the company so that?
Oh yeah.
Yeah.
It takes a lot of time, a lot
of thought that comes out of my strategies.
How do you see, what
do you see as very important?
Okay.
So I'm the process girl here.
So my bias is that you
should have SOPs out of the gate.
You should have, you should document,
you should put them in place.
It doesn't mean that they live forever.
But it's so much easier to do business
when you know what you need to do,
and you know and you have guidelines and
you have a place that you can refer to
and you can send people back to.
It's easy to find worth in all the other work,
but what will happen is if
you don't put policies in place
and you don't put process in place,
inevitably you're going to spend more time having to stop
and address issues that you wouldn't have
had to if you had them in place.
And I think the earlier you do
that, the better that you are at them.
They certainly can be changed.
They're not there forever.
I agree with that, and I think that
it doesn't mean you have to be bureaucratic, right?
But I think process is important.
Again, back to early commons routines,
so people have guidelines and guardrails for work.
I think the thing that makes organizations, people effective
is having really clarity around when things are wrong,
whether it's at home or whether it's
in a relationship or whether it's at work,
the degree to which you can
be clear about what your expectations are,
clear about what your own needs are,
clear about what the outcome is you want to be.
Always focus on clarity, I
think, always makes things better.
It may lead to some conflict, but the conflict also,
if it helps you get to better clarity,
you're going to be in a better place.
Conflict is good if it
gets you to a better place.
Your first question, though, I just, my own
personal advice to you, you just be you.
Exactly.
You know, female or whatever, you be your authentic self.
And that'll take you a whole long way.
Lots of questions.
Good.
Yeah.
Thank you.
I would like to be
back again to the co-founder's conflict,
where you have the different set of people, right?
You have a co-founder and a co-founder.
And you have the same decision all the time,
the value, technical model starts going down,
and business, co-founder starts getting down.
And that naturally creates some kind
of insecurity for the other person, right?
Any part of the experience, how you actually
try to solve that particular situation or experience?
Well, I think that, you know, personally, I've
been in some situations where I would help
facilitate that, okay?
But usually when someone asked me to do that,
that was already, you know, more of a problem
than you would have wanted it to be, right?
So I would say, you know, if you,
that in business, okay, you're going to have that
natural conflict that's going to come about
because of sometimes the amount of time people
take to develop the technology or the quality
with which they will and what the go-to-market
needs might be.
And so that's part of it.
Yeah.
And I think that's what happens.
But I think that having, you know, being able to
have a dialogue and be able to try to problem
solve together, if you have outside financial
advisors or, you know, professors or whoever
is helping you get going, you know,
chances are you have trusted resources around you.
If you had a trusted resource that you
both parties, you know, respected, you know, hopefully
that person could help.
Maybe even just facilitate a dialogue to
help you come to more common ground.
I think it's important to understand,
know when to ask for help.
And also to be honest always in these interactions.
You know, sometimes we get angry and, you
know, walk away and, you know, you may not
really have really gotten to the issue.
One of the things I used to always try to
do, I still try to do this in my life, when
I'm having a conflict with someone.
I'd say, well, do you have any, when
we were done, do you have any undelivered communication?
Chances are more stuff came out, you know,
when you say, you know, is there anything
else here you have to say?
And you're sure there's nothing else you're holding back.
Well, maybe they were, right?
And a person said to me once, when
you take what's covert, what's behind, and you can
make it overt, then you can problem solve.
And a lot of times people don't always honestly dialogue.
So hopefully that helps.
But I think don't be afraid to ask for
help with people that you know and trust and who
that other party would trust as well.
Some more hands.
Yeah.
I thought I would play in here.
But the problem might not have passed
but I'd like to pose to you.
And then I'll tell you how I resolved it.
So this may not be atypical for a
kind of companies to come out of here.
So one of my co-founders.
My co-founder, I was in the state of Kentucky.
I had a social worker, he
was very much a social worker.
was a MIT computer science professor,
a brilliant guy, and just fantastic.
I began to notice over time we weren't meeting schedules.
And the team seemed to not be functioning well.
So I started asking people, why are we behind?
But what slowly came out was people said,
and I had to piece this together.
Well, I go to the co-founder, and I say,
here's what I'm proposing to do.
And immediately, I'm so throwing in the side,
well, did you take a nap?
And they would feel like, let me scoot.
Just because you said, you know,
the post-docs are going to go
through that motivated and throwing in time.
And so they would go back.
And over time, we're afraid to bring issues forward,
because we're going to lose .
So once I said, what if
you do a situation like that?
And I'll tell you what.
I'm going to do it.
Well, I think what you have
to do in a situation like that
is you have to tell the person what they're doing.
Now, they may not want to hear it.
And sometimes, people, sometimes their egos are such, right,
that they have to be better, smarter, whatever.
Sometimes, they just are smarter and think faster.
And that's sort of where they go, right?
A lot of times, I think,
when people are going to be doing
things, they're going to be doing things that they're not
going to be doing.
And sometimes, when people do
that, they aren't aware of it.
And sometimes, by bringing a level of awareness to it,
it makes it better.
If it's really driven by ego,
chances are that won't fix it.
But I think the other way, potentially.
I don't know if you guys
have any other thoughts on that.
Yeah.
I took a class on radical candor.
And it is phenomenal, if any of you are interested.
But it's just that.
It's having, you know, a lot of people.
Yeah.
You know, very honest conversation and putting
it in the room in a kind way.
Not in a, you know, not in a mean way.
In a kind way.
So it's very valuable.
Is that what you did, Jo?
I'm laughing because my first response
would be, you're making everybody feel stupid,
stupid.
You know?
I can't believe you're saying that.
But that's Kim's kind.
I think that's what I
did once I figured it out.
A lot of people figure it out.
So I think it's great.
I think it's great.
But sometimes you don't know what's going on.
And I've talked with him about it.
And it wasn't ego.
It was just the way he was.
And so I said, well, why don't we try this.
Whenever you have meetings with the team,
one-on-one, you have an idea or two.
And, you know, people come and
say, well, did you think of this?
And I'm sure that I was
just as stupid as they were.
And I'm going out, I push
back a little bit against the idea.
And I'm going to try this.
And I'm going to push back against the idea.
And I don't think about it.
I try to go beyond that.
You know?
But I'm not going to go beyond that.
I'm going to keep going.
I'm going to try this.
And, you know, people come and say,
well, what did you think of this?
And I would show them I
was just as stupid as they were.
And I would point out,
I'd push back a little bit against them
and sort of get to something,
so they'd realize they weren't the stupid ones.
And so we did that for a while.
It was painful, but eventually we understood.
That's good.
You know, if you don't figure this out,
we're going to get anywhere because, you know,
and by the way, some
of the stuff you asked for
was a little off our time because, you know,
it was so brilliant.
So we worked it out that way.
But it was, it took a while,
and that's all I can say.
Well, he learned, so.
So I was stupid, too.
Vivian, you mentioned bureaucracy a little bit,
and I was wondering,
like, what level of a company
does that start to be
a concern from an HR perspective,
and how do you avoid the pitfalls
of falling into kind of the bureaucratic tendency?
That's a good question.
Well, the nature of the beast of what we do
is some of it is, you know,
HR function has so much to it,
and a lot of it is,
there's administrative, right,
because we're paying people.
We have to figure out where we slot people
in an organization.
You know, you want to make sure you have fairness,
and that you have benefits, you know,
and then there's the whole other side of it
that's more helping your business be successful.
So, you know, I think that I always liked,
Michelle can probably speak to this more.
I think if you had systems,
and this is where I think technology can help,
if it's managed appropriately right
when you're structuring,
and putting systems in place,
and I'm all for putting systems in place,
and process in place early on,
because it's much easier to build upon it
than it is to go back.
I joined one company.
It was 500 people when I joined.
There was no,
everybody was doing everything on spreadsheets.
I mean, it was ridiculous,
and everybody, you know,
there was no job structure,
and to go back and retrofit that
was, you know, just crazy,
but I think you can do it in a way
if you do it early on to keep it simple,
but yet do the things that you need to do
from a reporting compliance and fairness standpoint,
and I don't know what you would add on that,
because Michelle, that's what she,
her wheelhouse.
Yeah, you know, I also think you're at
a major advantage right now with AI.
So, you know, when I think back to,
you know, when I was kind of starting
to put businesses operationally strong,
I was starting from scratch,
and now you have so much technology
at your fingertips that help you,
you know, do things even easier.
So when you were talking about,
you know, policies and documentation,
I mean, my gosh, you could, you know,
ask ChatGPT to throw up, you know,
a policy for you, and then it's not,
you take that, and then you iterate on it,
and you make it, you know, you make it yours,
but it's a starting place,
and it takes such little time.
The other thing I would say to you is
technology is your friend,
you can have really low-cost solutions
that help put that infrastructure in place
that creates really the basis for fairness,
because your business is, if it's successful,
it's going to grow, you're going to hire more people,
you don't want to have to stop
and take the time to go backwards
and put things in place so that you can ensure
that you're, you know, it's not noise for your employees,
you know you're paying your employees effectively,
you're giving them the benefits that are the right,
you know, benefits for them,
you're staying compliant because the government and,
you know, legal is going to want to make sure
you're doing all of the things that are,
you're staying legally compliant,
and there's a lot of
opportunity for you to do it
with low-cost technology today.
Yeah, I think the bureaucracy comes in, honestly,
in organizations that get too hierarchical.
I believe in organizations being very flat,
I believe in, you know, letting your decision making be
as low in the organization as possible.
People are more engaged, they're more empowered,
and generally they know what needs to be done.
But that's something as an organization grows,
sometimes you get away from
it, and sometimes it's necessary.
But I've seen more bureaucracy get put into organizations.
Sometimes people like to empire build
because it makes them more important, right?
And so, you know, I always believed in flatter,
and not a lot of hierarchy.
I think the test is
when it doesn't make sense anymore,
then you know you've got too much in.
And it, you know, 130,000 employees,
I can't tell you how many times it's, you know,
somebody will tell me, well, Kim,
this is what the process is.
Okay, the process is going to prohibit us
from either meeting customer needs or driving revenue.
It just doesn't make sense anymore.
It's just that, I'm oversimplifying, but it, you know,
so ask yourself the question, is
it getting in the way of,
you know, what's the best
way to get people to work?
Is it getting in the way of, you
know, the best way to get people to work?
Is it getting in the way
of you actually running your business?
That all makes sense, very good.
Yeah.
How pushable did it get?
I started my car business about a couple years ago,
and as a founder of Well-Being,
I have to learn a lot to do things
that I didn't want to start to learn.
And of course, all the time,
I was actually very responsible
for the process of doing this,
and now I'm in a
position where I am very able,
and I found it super difficult
to actually know how to do it,
because it does not matter how much people work,
and how much you love the business work,
it just doesn't meet my standards.
And I find it so difficult
to keep myself away from stepping in.
It was my baby, and I don't know,
but I try to, but it's difficult.
So I don't know what
the rest of the day was.
Well, I've seen that movie.
Every day, yep.
Yeah.
It's hard, right?
I think so, as you lead, okay?
One of the hardest things to do
is you kind of have to turn over
a little bit of control
of your destiny to others, right?
And that's hard to do.
And you have to trust,
and you have to have the right people,
and all of that doesn't happen overnight.
But it takes,
it's a personal growth to be able to do that,
because we want to control the things ourselves,
especially if it's something that we've built, right?
And I think it's very
hard for founders to let go.
It's literally their baby, right?
And having that balance is, I think,
will always be difficult for anybody that's founded
an organization and has to stay with it.
And I think hopefully the
key is having people around you,
like in the example that Joe gave,
that'll help you and give you feedback
to know maybe when you need to jump in
and maybe when you need to pull back.
That's, I think, the best advice I could give you.
Yeah.
I think it's reminding yourself, too,
that doing it yourself all the time
is not a scalable model, right?
So, I mean, that's the hard reality of it is,
is this scalable if I continue to do it myself?
Yeah.
And you'll burn out.
You'll get tired.
You'll get angry.
You'll start snapping.
People will leave.
They're not going to want to be around you.
All of those things.
Trust me, high control right here.
I have four children.
Trust me.
I have learned that it's better to let go
and better to help when they need it.
Yeah.
female male anger
at好
and hi
you
and it's time to expand your lean further.
So your boundary team is not as responsible
to hire that talent, but they also feel
that they might find someone
who's better than them at it.
Now, you're trusting the boundary team,
but you also have that sense
that they would be doing this.
How does the founder navigate from that?
It's a very problematic scenario.
It is a problem, yeah.
You wanna jump?
Yeah.
I think you have to stay
close to the team that's hiring
to have a common ground
in terms of what you're hiring.
There's a level of letting them do it
and trying to go through the candidate selection process,
but also keeping your finger,
we talk about our general management team,
anybody who's in a GM role,
you're an inch off the ground.
So you're keeping a close enough level to the detail
and how they're hiring or what they're looking for.
You'll see the insecurities in it.
If it's there, and quite honestly,
how you quickly rectify it, you take it much more
on a personal level, helping them feel good
about what they're hiring and the experiences
that they can convey to the new hires
and things of that nature.
You can bolster their ego up so that the insecurity
that's there is a little bit less.
But I think as you're growing, you probably wanna stay
a little bit closer to who you're hiring
and who is making the hiring decision.
So I think it's important
to make those decisions for you
because it's costly.
I also think that in
all the companies I've worked in,
we had a very elaborate hiring process.
I mean, almost everybody and their mother would interview
the people that were coming in.
And the good news about that
is it does give you more buy-in
for the candidate ultimately.
But sometimes it lengthens the process.
I've seen us lose candidates because our hiring process
included work that was too inclusive.
The other thing that I think
is important, and I think this is
a very important point, is that the hiring manager
should make that final decision.
And I think having clarity around that,
yes, I'll take all your input, but ultimately,
say you see a candidate that is higher skilled
and you know that's gonna compliment the team,
some of the other people
that might have been a peer
may not have supported that.
They may have felt threatened by something like that.
So I think real clarity
around who the decision maker is.
And I think a group that's
going to be able to do that,
I think that's a really important thing.
And I think a group think isn't always the best.
I think it's good to take everyone's input,
but then you make your own decision.
Another question regarding interpersonal relationships
and the .
On this scenario, you actually responded to him about that.
You can have a judgment from everyone in the audience
to have with them all an
opinion and discuss it with them.
But I've seen a scenario where obviously,
the founder has authority.
And although everyone's sitting in front
of him on a round table,
people are feeling that if they talk about office politics,
that's disrupting their normal operations or productivity.
And the reason being if someone goes to the founder,
they fear that mentioning that would obviously
have the other person mentioning to the founder
that this is the reason that
he's not operating at least one unit
at all.
So that's another scenario where if you're
discussing someone, but you are giving everyone's opinion,
you still have to decide who
you lean on in such a situation.
I think that that's hard.
And I can see how
that can be an issue, especially
in a small organization.
I think that over time, you
will have, or the founder will have,
you know, you will always have a more trusted colleague.
Right?
But trust goes both ways.
And I think that I would
judge people by their behavior and actions.
And if someone is not operating
in good faith or breaching confidences
or whatever the case may be, you
know, I would think about my level
of trust with that person.
I would try to talk about
it or get it to be better.
But I think that those are human
dynamics that are always going to happen.
Right?
And there's going to be people that
you know you can just count on.
And I might weight that person's
input more heavily based on my experience
and their honesty and what have you, if that's helpful.
Yeah.
So all these issues discussed are quite
complex because they relate to human behavior.
Yeah.
there are a lot of different emotional
and stuff like that that the current age
of AI have to wonder, like
in the influence of all this experience,
all these insights that we have.
When people are sitting here looking
for a system, is there any particular,
like a tool that you recommend, resource
that depends, like myself in the field,
of course, a lot of this
year , and at the same time,
you said it's kind of the same
because you spoiled, or you spoiled data.
Of course it's nothing specific.
Everything is my own thought.
Oh.
So yeah mhm.
that some results out there in the future.
On the very basis that sometimes you would like
to get some guidance.
There's a lot of different things.
So why don't you guys
talk about some of your experiences
and I can jump in on that.
Yeah, there are a lot.
Do I believe that there's an assistant
that would take over our role today?
No, I don't.
But I'm an embracer of AI.
I know that there are
folks that are nervous about it
and rightfully so.
But I do see a lot of potential coming.
And this may be more than
what you're looking for right now.
But I have spent a lot of time with LinkedIn
and in the hiring space with LinkedIn and LinkedIn Learning.
And the technology that they have embedded
in their process,
their product that you can use is extraordinary.
So it's not quite an assistant yet
that you may be looking for.
You know, outside of like ChatGPT or, you know,
the bots that are kind of popping up everywhere.
But from a platform perspective,
that gives you good guidance
at a relatively reasonable price.
LinkedIn has a lot embedded in it
and they're really investing in their AI.
They're really putting a lot of effort
into the technology.
They're really getting the right people
in the right places and doing the right things.
And they're really investing in their AI technologies.
I think from a self-development standpoint,
there are things that you can do too.
I think that, you know, hopefully we're all a work
in progress as long as
we are on this earth, right?
And so I think it's important to try
to be as self-aware as we can.
So if there's programs that, you know, we participated in,
we made an investment in
the company we worked in together.
This model still exists and it's one
of the most powerful models
I ever worked for, worked with.
I still use it.
It's called process communication model.
And it's very similar.
It's sort of like a basis of a Myers-Briggs.
People seem to know that personality type.
But this talks about how
people evolve and change over time.
It also talks about how people react under stress.
You know, at one point many years ago,
I was certified to teach this program.
But we incorporated it into,
you know, our work and training
and our management development and all that.
And then I did it in three different companies.
And it really helped for a
level of self-awareness first of all.
But also helped people for self-understanding
and working together.
And there may be some better tools out there now.
But I think the degree to we can work
on our own self-development and that will come
through.
And that's something that we
can do through our own work.
Not so much, you know, AI
can maybe give us some tools
that we can look at for that to use
for a level of self-awareness.
I think that's helpful too.
So my understanding of that, the personal human employees
that you hire in the company are crucial to forming
the culture of the startup company.
So let's say, hypothetically, you start a company
and you're hiring your first few employees.
And you're interviewing someone and you think
that they're very technically qualified for the position.
But you're not sure if
you can fit into the culture
that you're trying to cultivate.
Firstly, is there anything you can do about that
to sort of meld them with the .
Or secondly, do you need
to sort of find a way
to make sure that you're hiring someone that you think
might be less technically qualified but better fit
for the culture that you're trying to create?
That's hard.
It is a hard one.
I have a bias.
It's just like a spouse though.
You're never going to change them.
No.
Yeah.
So I don't know.
I'm a gut hirer.
So if I feel in
my gut that that person's not
going to meld with the rest
of my team, I never hire them.
Regardless of what their technical acumen is.
But that may not be the case for everyone else.
I'll give you another example of, I agree with Michelle.
I think in a small environment, it's
critical to have the connection.
However, I will give you
an example of we have somebody
in the company that I work with.
He's like mass spectrometry god.
And he drives us around.
He drives us crazy.
But because he is who he
is, so a couple of things.
One, if they're so technically competent, two things
that I'll tell you.
If they're going to advance your technology
and you can figure out how to manage them
and manage the relationship, OK.
Second, if you want to keep them out
of the hands of your competitors, OK.
So I think it's a balance
of how disruptive their behavior would
be to your culture versus the benefit of the capabilities
they bring.
Yeah, that's fair.
And maybe like the instance that Joan talked about,
is it something, is it the core of that person?
Is it a character flaw?
If it's a character flaw, those aren't easy to fix.
And if someone is mean
spirited or so egoistic or narcissistic
or any of those things, even they might be brilliant,
it would be toxic.
But if it's sometimes people are oblivious
or they're so focused on something
or they're not aware that they're doing something,
then that can work.
But Kim's advice is good too.
Sometimes you put that person over in a box.
How bad do you need it?
Yeah.
And what is that person's needs too, right?
That person might just want to go develop the technology.
They may not care.
They might not care so much about the interactions.
Who knows?
I don't know if we have, do
you have any questions for the people
online at all?
No?
OK.
There's someone up there.
Right there.
Right up back.
Nope.
Cheat.
Right up behind you.
Behind you.
Yeah.
I got it.
Oh.
Yeah.
Go ahead.
So I was just following up to that question of,
I mean, sometimes, OK, I'm still young,
and so I don't have so much experience.
But I've seen people change over time.
I've seen that they were very mean before,
but then certain life experiences made the change.
So in that aspect, do you think people can change?
Yeah.
Because they were not easy to work with,
but then certain things happened
in life, and then they changed.
Yeah.
And what other examples have you seen,
and what kind of close engage would you put?
I think people can.
So that model that I told you I like,
the premise of how people change, and this
is true to my own life experience, OK?
People change under periods of profound stress
when their own needs aren't being met anymore.
So you have to do something different,
because life isn't working for you.
And it isn't necessarily, I mean, sometimes,
it happens with a tragedy, unfortunately.
Sometimes someone dies.
Sometimes someone gets ill.
And sometimes life's just not working for you,
and so you have to do something different.
I have seen people change with that.
I've also seen people go through real tragedies, OK?
And they were still wonderful, right?
And they didn't let the
tragedy get them down or whatever.
And so as human beings, I think we are remarkable
in that we can still change,
and we can learn and whatever.
But I do think that's when I've seen
the change happen with people.
And sometimes people aren't successful.
I've seen a person that was
very good at what she did.
She got fired from a lot of jobs because she
didn't work well with others.
She was, but the quality
of her work was really good.
Yeah.
And this person now is, I've
known her almost her whole life.
She's, I'd say, in her mid-50s.
She's finally come to it
that it was her own need
to have high achievement and not
be collegial that got in the way
and caused her to lose her jobs over time.
And she's been much more successful later in life,
but she's kind of learned what she had to learn.
I think what I would ask you
is, people change when they want to
or experience changes.
And as founders, do you want
to take the time, the precious time,
at the beginning of your journey to
hire people that may have to change
to fit into your organization?
Yeah.
I have two questions.
I have a question.
Before that, I would like to start
with the very few small group of people.
And they are very, very skilled.
And they're not familiar with
the business world, probably not
at all.
But they have a very good product.
And they are very good at what they do,
just not have the knowledge in that area.
So at that stage, probably having an HR person
is not the main concern in the pattern.
Maybe having a lawyer you need to find.
I would be having an accountant who
would like to do the taxes anyway.
When's an appropriate time for someone
to start being a hiring an HR person?
And why is that good?
So the number of people who are working
the company, the type of the company, or the stage.
I would like to do
some of that at that time.
And second, many people already talked about the culture.
Yeah.
Again, this is a term that not everybody
is necessarily familiar with.
Because that can affect how the whole system operates,
or business plan, or marketing strategy.
So for people who are not familiar with this area,
what are some questions that they
should think about when they're in the process of choosing
their culture?
And you could give us an example, maybe
a conference that you already know,
so that we can manage that.
And .
We have a bunch of questions.
I'm going to let you
guys talk about the culture part.
And I'll talk about who you hire.
I think that it depends what your needs are.
If early on you need some help in terms
of thinking of your structure, thinking
about what you want your culture to be, or whatever,
I would say work with a trusted advisor,
or people to help you do that.
I did have a question about the culture.
I'm sorry.
I did some consulting and
work with a venture capital company
that had invested in the last company I worked in.
And I would do some sessions with those folks.
What I found, and this is just on the basis
of my own experience, around 25 to 50 people
in an organization, you needed some sort of outside advice.
Typically.
They would bring in, have outside legal advice
if they needed it, and hire
that sort of on a contract basis.
They tended to bring in a financial person
before they would bring in a human resource person.
And probably that is more the need.
You have to pay people.
You have to do some of
the more financial things early on.
The one thing I would say, though,
is a lot of times
in most of these early companies,
when they do hire their HR person,
they have the HR person work for the finance person.
Don't do that.
It really is better to have that function separate,
because it's as important in a different way,
and to give that person sort of equal status.
So that's what I would say about that.
I think that second part of your culture question,
maybe these guys can chime in on.
Yeah, I think that when you think about culture
and what are some of the questions that you ask,
you go back to, again, what
is your mission or the value
of the company?
Or your product?
How do you take that into your employee population?
How do you want it to feel?
What are going to be the common values
that you have amongst your employees?
Is it level of integrity?
Is it the amount of intensity that you have?
How do you want to be known?
And then I think you take that into, OK,
how do you take what
you're producing, you take the values,
and you enable a level of excitement amongst yourself
and your colleagues.
Yeah.
And you can kinda ask, how
do you fix some of that?
And that's OK, that's very, that's possible.
That's simple, but it's not
going to do you more work
for your organization.
That's a nice way of saying, it isn't you.
These are just three words that I think
are great for you.
And if you're going to continue to read about yourself,
or just something really specific,
then I think the most useful way for you
I agree with Kim. I think that it's an exercise you have to go through. What is important to you as a company?
So to those founders, what do they get up for every day? What is important for them to see in their employees every day?
And I do. I think you put it, you know, pen to paper and you write it
down and it's your values and your mission. And I think your culture comes out of that.
And I wish I knew how to spell his last name, but I, so the last company that I was
at, it was a smaller company and it was a conglomerate of a bunch of small companies that were bought.
And what I first realized is each one of them
had very separate cultures of the, you know, the acquire companies.
And so I was like, well, I'm going to go with the conglomerate of the small company that came in. And so we were really
trying to rebrand and how do we allow them to keep their culture, but also kind of have much more of an open corporate culture.
I had somebody come in who used to be the culture officer of Facebook and he talked about, he's fascinating. And he talked
about working with Mark Zuckerberg and, you know, Zuckerberg's whole philosophy was I want every employee to feel like Facebook is their company.
And so that's how they started
on new hire onboarding is this.
So we started with one
or PDF of the把它, two blocks.
Of what we're working on now and it's a little bit of developing process, but the whole back to goal of
basically uso of these ideas of let's just build on top of each other to embrace, which is important to us.
Now I was looking at it
kind of your workbook and it shake.
And at first, I was
like, this is just the space.
But now we realize how much more,
this is now you also the conglomerate.
unknown匁 later.
And so it, we don't want, so there was like, that can
most people do the same thing, butном with one or PDF version.
fascinating. You could look up Facebook
creating culture. It's just kind of neat.
The thing is, as a leader, as a CEO in
particular, you have so much power. You really do. And you
have the power to create that organization. People
will look to you to create the culture
and what have you. And in the strongest cultures that
I was a part of, I'd like to think that I
was a part of it. And I was. But it was really
the CEO that set the tone. And he or she, how they
behaved and what have you. And the really good
CEOs, as the companies got, they never lost their
relationships to the employees in the company.
And they didn't have the hierarchy. They would
drop into people's offices and they would travel if
it was a global company. And one of the nicest
thing about...
when we were at RSA security together, we were global
and I don't know, 20 some odd countries or whatever.
You could go to RSA Japan, you could go to
RSA Australia, go RSA Vancouver, you could go RSA India,
you could go RSA Ireland, and of course it
had its culture for where country you were in,
but it was still the RSA culture in terms
of how people treated one another, what was important,
what was valued, what was rewarded. That's part of
also how you set the tone for your culture.
Well, we've come up on the time. This is
fantastic. I've done this course for a number of years.
I've been around the track a few times. This panel
is always a great session because I always learn something.
Thank you.
That's something important. There's
been a lot imparted here.
I hope you think about
it as you grow your companies.
Thank you.
Thank you very much.
I really enjoy it.
Thank you unless you stop working, so I'm
glad to have dean and Wade here with us.
You can address any questions you may want to, certainly.
Don't be questioners.
vocal